Guide to the Oscar Hijuelos Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Oscar Hijuelos Papers,
1974-2005
[Bulk Dates: 1977-2003].
Hijuelos, Oscar.
16 linear ft. (38 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#1490
5706615
The bulk of the Oscar Hijuelos Papers consists of notes, multiple drafts, and galley proofs for six of Hijuelos' novels, all written and published between 1977 and 2002; several short stories; an unpublished version of Mr. Ives' Christmas; and the musical version of The Mambo Kings Play Songs of Love. The collection also includes research materials for the novels, translations, limited correspondence with editors and friends, and a deposition relating to a lawsuit.
History
Oscar Hijuelos was born to Cuban immigrants in 1951 in the Morningside Heights neighborhood of New York City. He attended public schools and then Bronx Community College; he later enrolled at The City College of New York and received a B.A. in 1975 and an M.F.A. in 1976. As a graduate student in writing, he worked with Donald Barthelme and Susan Sontag.
After completing his studies, Hijuelos earned his living by working during the day in an advertising agency. Before and after hours, he wrote short stories and started writing his first novel, Our House in the Last World. He soon gained recognition for his work: a group of his stories was included in the 1978 anthology Best of Pushcart Press III, and he won a scholarship to the prestigious Breadloaf Writers Conference in Vermont in 1980. His debut novel garnered several awards--The American Academy of Arts and Letters Rome Prize, a fellowship from the National Endowment for the Arts, and an Ingram-Merrill fellowship. These grants allowed Hijuelos to leave his advertising job and devote himself to writing fiction. During his 1985 writing residency in Rome, Hijuelos started writing The Mambo Kings Play Songs of Love, which was published in 1989 and won The Pulitzer Prize for Fiction in 1990--the first novel by a Latino writer to win the prize. Arne Glimcher adapted the novel into the feature film The Mambo Kings in 1992 and, in collaboration with Carlos Franzetti, a stage musical in 2005.
Since the enormous success of The Mambo Kings Play Songs of Love, Hijuelos has written five novels, all of which depict the lives of Cuban-born or Cuban-descended characters living in the United States: The Fourteen Sisters of Emilio Montez O'Brien (1993), Mr. Ives' Christmas (1995), Empress of the Splendid Season (1999), A Simple Habana Melody (2002), and Dark Dude (2008). Hijuelos has also contributed to several anthologies of Latino literature. He has taught at Hofstra University and currently teaches creative writing at Duke University. He lives on the Upper West Side of Manhattan.
Scope and Content
The collection contains research materials, notes, and manuscripts of several short stories and six novels written by Hijuelos between 1974 and 2003. The research materials consist of clippings and photocopies of articles, photographs, and drawings from newspapers, magazines, and books; print-outs of articles from the Internet; and musical lyrics and an album liner. Typed drafts of some of the stories and all of the novels include extensive notes and revisions from Hijuelos and his teachers (Susan Sontag and Donald Barthelme) and editors (Jonathan Galassi of Farrar, Straus, and Giroux, among others); multiple galley proofs of the novels include editorial queries and corrections. The musical version of The Mambo Kings contains correspondence between Hijuelos and director Arne Glimcher. The collection also contains a small amount of personal and professional correspondence, a deposition by Hijuelos relating to a lawsuit brought against him in 1992, and a copy of an interview with Hijuelos.
Arrangement
The material is arranged chronologically.
Subjects
Hijuelos, Oscar.; Cuba--Fiction.; Cuban Americans--Fiction.
Access Restrictions
Available for faculty, students, and researchers engaged in scholarly publication projects.
Acquisition
Purchased in 2006
Finding aid is available in the repository and online
- Oscar Hijuelos Papers
  - General
    - Correspondence, 1979-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Deposition of Oscar Hijuelos, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Printed material--Interview with Hijuelos, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings
    - Our House in the Last World (1983)
      - Drafts, 1970s-1983, (5 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 3 to 8)
      - Drafts, 1970s-1983, (6 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Drafts, 1970s-1983, (5 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1970s-1983, (5 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1970s-1983, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Chapter Pages, Illustrations, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "Reading for Peace," 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Segments submitted to Susan Sontag, circa 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Mambo Kings Play Songs of Love (1990)
      - Drafts, 1980s, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 6 to 8)
      - Drafts, 1980s, (5 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1980s, (5 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1980s, (4 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1980s, (4 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Galleys, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Galleys, 1989, (5 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Galleys, 1989, (5 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Musical--Drafts, 1996-2003, (6 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Musical--Drafts, 1996-2003, (5 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Musical--Drafts, 1996-2003, (5 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Musical--Drafts, 1996-2003, (3 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1 to 3)
    - The Fourteen Sisters of Emilio Montez O'Brien (1993)
      - Drafts, 1980s-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1980s-1993, (4 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1980s-1993, (4 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1980s-1993, (5 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1980s-1993, (3 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Mr. Ives' Christmas (1995)
      - Drafts, 1990s (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (4 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (4 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (5 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (4 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (4 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (5 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (5 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Translation of opening chapter, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Empress of the Splendid Season (1999)
      - Drafts, 1996-1998, (3 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 4 to 6)
      - Drafts, 1996-1998, (4 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1996-1998, (4 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 1997-1998, (4 Folders) (Box 30, Folder 1 to 4)
    - A Simple Habana Melody (2002)
      - Notebook, 2001 (1 Folder) (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - Drafts, 2001 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      - Drafts, 2001, (5 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 2001, (5 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 2001, (5 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Drafts, 2001, (4 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Drafts, 2001-2002, (2 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Galleys, 2002, (3 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 3 to 5)
      - Galleys, 2002, (5 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Galleys, 2002, (6 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Galleys, 2002, (2 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Translation, 2002, (2 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Introduction, 2003 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Other writings
      - "Chameleon," 1980s (Box 38, Folder 6)
      - "Precision," undated (Box 38, Folder 7)
      - "Sleep," 1980s (Box 38, Folder 8)
      - Article on August Wilson--Drafts, 2005 (Box 38, Folder 9)